{"tossups": [{"question": "Anthony, Duke of Brabant, arrived late to this battle, where he used a trumpeter's flag to make a surcoat. One leader at this battle ordered the mass execution of prisoners after Ysembart [[EE-zem-barht]] stole the victor's crown from a baggage train. This battle, which occurred on St. Crispin\u2019s Day, led to the marriage of Charles VI's daughter and its victor in the Treaty of Troyes [[TWAH]]. For ten points, name this victory for Henry V during the Hundred Years\u2019 War, which included heavy use of longbows.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Agincourt</u></b> [[AH-zhin-corh]] (accept Battle of <b><u>Azincourt</u></b>; be lenient on pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1968, this artist was shot by radical feminist Valerie Solanas, which may have contributed to his death nineteen years later. In 2013, this artist\u2019s <em>Silver Car Crash (Double</em> <em>Disaster)</em> sold for $105 million. This artist\u2019s Factory in New York City hosted a film studio, an assembly line for lithograph and silk-screening production, and drug-fueled parties featuring celebrities and free-thinkers. For ten points, name this pop artist best known for his <em>Marilyn Diptych</em> and depictions of Campbell\u2019s Soup Cans.", "answer": "Andy <b><u>Warhol</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One candidate in this presidential election year secured nomination on the second ballot after the withdrawal of Samuel J. Randall. This was the first election year during which Belva Lockwood appeared on the ballot. The rallying cry \"Burn this letter\" during this election year was popularized after a discovery of some papers by James Mulligan. The slogan \"Ma, Ma, Where\u2019s my Pa?\" mocked the philandering of this year's election winner.  For ten points, name this election year in which James G. Blaine lost to Grover Cleveland.", "answer": "<b><u>1884</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As part of this project, Kevin Kruse wrote a work titled for how one policy \u201cCaused a Traffic Jam.\u201d Jake Silverstein wrote a \u201cclarification\u201d of this project, which was the subject of a proposal by Tom Cotton to ban federal funding to schools that taught it. Nikole Hannah-Jones developed this project, which included pieces on Crispus Attucks and Phillis Wheatley. The arrival of a privateer in colonial Virginia inspired the date that names, for ten points, what ongoing initiative from <em>The New York Times Magazine</em> focusing on slavery\u2019s impact on America?", "answer": "The <b><u>1619</u></b> Project", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A shield logo representing one of these institutions depicts a set of staples on the right half in honor of its co-founder, Seth Staples. A process called \u201celenchus\u201d [[eh-LEN-koos]] provided the basis for a practice at these institutions that is often paired with one that relies on casebooks. Plato\u2019s <em>Theaetetus</em> [[thee-ih-TEE-tuss]] may have introduced a method of \u201cargument by refutation\u201d used at these institutions named for Socrates. Moot court competitions are held at, for ten points, what educational institutions at which students prepare for the bar exam?", "answer": "<b><u>Law school</u></b>s (prompt on \"colleges,\" \"universities,\" or \"schools\")", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "After this man was killed in Chicago in 1969, one group went on a bombing spree and planned to bomb Fort Dix. The month before his death, this man stated, \"What we\u2019re going to try to do, is we\u2019re going to try to rap and educate\" in a speech about class struggle at Northern Illinois University. After this man's death, Bobby Rush took his former position and said \"we have to arm ourselves.\" William O'Neal drugged this man with barbiturates for the FBI, after which the Chicago police killed him and Mark Clark. For ten points, name this Black Panther leader.", "answer": "Frederick \"Fred\" <b><u>Hampton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man saved his wingman, \"Jig Dog\" Ramage [[RAM-uhj]], while serving as a fighter pilot. NASA presents an annual Technology in Education Award named for this man. This man was part of a group including Wally Schirra and Deke Slayton and followed Yuri Gagarin in a feat on the <em>Freedom 7</em>, part of the Redstone 3 mission. The oldest man to walk on the moon as part of the Apollo 14 mission, this man hit two golf balls on the moon. The head of the first crewed Project Mercury flight, for ten points, who was this astronaut, the first American to travel into space?", "answer": "Alan <b><u>Shepard</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man's assassination in Prague was the subject of a film co-written by Bertolt Brecht and Fritz Lang titled <em>Hangmen Also Die!</em>. This man implemented the <em>Einsatzgruppen</em> mobile death trucks, and he ran the death camp at Chelmno [[HELM-noh]]. This \"Blonde Beast\" called a meeting during which Adolf Eichmann created a list of Jews in various countries. This official organized the Wannsee [[VAHN-zay]] Conference, which united the German bureaucratic branches behind the Final Solution. For ten points, name this commander of the SS, the architect of the Holocaust.", "answer": "Reinhard <b><u>Heydrich</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Historian Ben Kiernan, who studied the abuses of this regime, estimates that between 1.67 and 1.87 million people died as a result of its genocidal policies. In 1975, this regime seized the U.S. merchant vessel SS <em>Mayaguez</em>. This political regime\u2019s Standing Committee included Brother Number Two and Brother Number Three, both of whom were later convicted by a UN tribunal for crimes against humanity. For ten points, name this Cambodian political regime supported by the Viet Cong and the Chinese Communist Party, which was led by Pol Pot.", "answer": "<b><u>Khmer Rouge</u></b> (accept <b><u>Democratic Kampuchea</u></b>; accept <b><u>Communist Party of</u></b> <b><u>Cambodia</u></b>; prompt on \"Kampuchea\" or \"Cambodia\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "On the first day of this event, the leader of the Escambray Rebellion was captured and immediately executed. In preparation for this event, the failed Operation Puma was meant to destroy the armed aircraft of the FAR. This event took place mostly on Gir\u00f3n [[hee-ROHN]] Beach and was executed by Brigade 2506, composed of exiles who intended to overthrow Fidel Castro. For ten points, name this failed 1961 landing operation, covertly supported by the Kennedy administration.", "answer": "<b><u>Bay of Pigs</u></b> Invasion (accept Invasi\u00f3n de <b><u>Bah\u00eda de Cochinos</u></b>; also accept Invasi\u00f3n de <b><u>Playa Gir\u00f3n</u></b> or <b><u>Batalla de Gir\u00f3n</u></b> before \"Gir\u00f3n\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A legend of these people told of how the captured Emperor Valens was burned in a farmhouse by their men during the Battle of Adrianople. A man descended from this tribe, Pelayo [[peh-LAI-oh]], was victorious at the Battle of Covadonga and ruled the last Iberian kingdom to hold out against the Umayyads. This tribe, which converted to Arianism, faced an attack from the forces of Emperor Honorius, culminating in the 410 Sack of Rome. For ten points, name this Gothic tribe led by King Alaric I, which conquered much of France and Spain.", "answer": "<b><u>Visigoth</u></b>s (prompt on \"Goth(s)\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This American military award was given posthumously to a set of three nurses that included Jane Rignel. In the order of precedence, this military decoration is between the Defense Superior Service Medal and the Distinguished Service Medal. This award was established in 1918 as a successor to the similarly-shaped \u201cCitation\u201d variety. For ten points, name this military decoration awarded for \"gallantry in action\" which, despite its name, is mostly gold.", "answer": "<b><u>Silver Star</u></b> Medal (or <b><u>SS</u></b>M)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This novel was its author's first published work after she quit working for the British Overseas Airways Corporation. In this novel, Dolphus Raymond pretends to drink alcohol while keeping Coca-Cola in a paper bag to fit in with the African-American community. A monument to a character in this novel stands in Monroeville, Alabama, which may have inspired its setting of Maycomb. In this novel, Bob Ewell\u2019s abuse of his daughter is revealed during a trial by Atticus Finch. A girl nicknamed Scout narrates, for ten points, what Harper Lee novel dealing with racial inequality?", "answer": "<em><b><u>To Kill a Mockingbird</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "This man invented the heliotrope to carry out a geodetic survey of the Kingdom of Hanover. Wilhelm Weber [[VEH-buh]] and this man constructed the first electromechanical telegraph. This man became the first to prove the quadratic reciprocity law, and in his PhD thesis, this man showed that all polynomials of order \"n\" have \"n\" roots, proving the fundamental theorem of algebra. For ten points, name this German mathematician from Brunswick who names the normal distribution.", "answer": "Carl Friedrich <b><u>Gauss</u> </b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "\" The Taniyama-Shimura conjecture was applied to Andrew Wiles's proof of a theorem by this man which went unproven for 358 years.", "answer": "Pierre de <b><u>Fermat</u></b> [[fehr-MAH]] (accept pronunciation as [[fehr-MAT]])", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "Despite its opponent being assisted by Ampud and Leustach R\u00e1t\u00f3t, this empire still won the Battle of Myriokephalon [[meer-ee-oh-KEHF-ah-lahn]]. During a march to Khorasan, the Ghaznavid army was constantly attacked by forces of this empire that won the Battle of Dandanaqan [[dahn-DAHN-uh-kun]]. Omar Khayyam served this empire, which oversaw the capture of Romanos IV Diogenes [[dai-AH-jin-ees]]. The Sultanate of Rum [[ROOM]] was an offshoot of this empire, which practiced Sunni Islam. One of the emirates into which this empire was broken served as the basis for the Ottomans. For ten points, name this medieval Anatolian empire.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Seljuk</u></b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This modern-day country's territories were made independent from Venice in the Treaty of Zadar. The second-largest city in this country was surveyed by Robert Adam in his studies of the ruins of Diocletian's Palace. This country's coastline was the location of the Republic of Ragusa, based out of Dubrovnik, and the Greek colony named Asp\u00e1lathos is today known as this country's city, Split. For ten points, name this country whose war of independence from 1991 to 1995 is known by natives as the \"Greater Serbian Aggression.\"", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Croatia</u></b> (or Republika <b><u>Hrvatska</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Croatia</u></b>)  In 1809, the territory of modern Croatia was annexed into the First French Empire following the Battle of Wagram during this war in which Austria was supported by a group of nations including the U.K., Portugal, Spain, Sardinia, and Sicily.  ANSWER: War of the <b><u>Fifth Coalition</u></b> (prompt on \"Napoleonic Wars\" or \"Coalition Wars\") (8) This man argued that excluding groups from the ballot in a democracy branded those groups with the \u201cstigma of inferiority.\u201d In one speech, this man asked if the \u201cprinciples\u2026embodied in that Declaration of Independence are extended to\u201d the central group and claimed that the Constitution did not intend one practice to be a \u201cgateway.\u201d This man, who asked \u201cWhat to the Slave is the Fourth of July?\" followed up his best known book with a sequel titled <em>My Bondage and My Freedom</em>. For ten points, name this abolitionist and author of a widely-read \"slave narrative.\"  ANSWER: Frederick <b><u>Douglass</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Riots erupted after the Treaty of Northampton promised the transfer of this</u></b> <b><u>object between two locations. In some stories, this object was used as a pillow by</u></b> <b><u>Jacob when he dreamed of a ladder that ascended to heaven. Kenneth MacAlpin</u></b> <b><u>brought this item from (+)</u> Iona [[ai-OH-nah]] to a location from which it was seized by Edward I in 1296. The most recent use of this object in its best known capacity occurred in 1953. Now found in (*) </b>Edinburgh Castle, this object is fixed to the base of a wooden Coronation Chair. For ten points, name this rock upon which Scottish monarchs have been crowned.", "answer": "<b><u>Stone of Scone</u></b> [[SKOON]] (accept <b><u>Coronation Stone</u></b> before \u201ccoronation\u201d is mentioned; accept <b><u>An Lia F\u00e1il</u></b>, <b><u>Stane o Scuin</u></b>, <b><u>Stone of Destiny</u></b>, <b><u>Tanist Stone</u></b>, or <b><u>Clach-na-</u><u>cinneamhain</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>People who engaged in this practice led a 1939 roadside demonstration in</u></b> <b><u>southeast Missouri under Owen Whitfield. This practice, which may have arisen in</u></b> <b><u>Adams County, Mississippi, was often accompanied by providing a portion of</u></b> <b><u>products as a (+)</u> lien, creating a cycle of debt. Mules were often rented out for this activity, which became the primary occupation of (*) </b>African-Americans in the South after the Civil War. For ten points, name this practice in which landowners took a portion of a worker\u2019s harvest in exchange for allowing them to work the land.", "answer": "<b><u>Sharecrop</u></b>ping (accept <b><u>Sharecrop</u></b>per(s); accept <b><u>Tenant Farm</u></b>ing; accept <b><u>Tenant Farm</u></b>er(s); prompt on \"agriculture\" or \"farming\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man engaged in an extensive feud over the nature of scientific</u></b> <b><u>experiments with Robert Boyle, and in his old age, this Englishman translated</u></b> <b><u>Thucydides. A crozier and a sword are held by a king comprised of human bodies in</u></b> <b><u>the frontispiece of a work by this man, which claims there is a single (+)</u> \u201crule of nature\u201d and originated the idea of the \u201cKingdom of Darkness.\u201d That work by this man claims that life without law would be (*) </b>\u201cnasty, brutish, and short.\u201d For ten points, name this political philosopher who wrote <em>Leviathan</em>.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Hobbes</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>The decision that led to this dispute arose from \u201cthe first news\u201d William</u></b> <b><u>Dickey received after returning from a gold prospecting effort along the Susitna</u></b> <b><u>River. A 2015 decision announced by Sally Jewel that aimed to end this dispute was</u></b> <b><u>criticized by Donald Trump as \u201ca great insult to (+)</u> Ohio,\u201d in reference to an earlier president. This dispute has involved the usage of a Koyukon term translating to \u201cthe (*) </b>high One.\u201d Concerning a location containing the Kahiltna glacier, for ten points, what is this dispute over how to refer to a certain Alaska mountain?", "answer": "<b><u>Denali</u></b>-Mount <b><u>McKinley</u><u>naming</u></b> dispute (accept clear-knowledge equivalents indicating disputes over the <b><u>name</u></b> of <b><u>Denali</u></b> or Mount <b><u>McKinley</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event occurred at 4 a.m. local time in order to appear at 10 p.m. in the</u></b> <b><u>eastern United States. This event was held in a stadium originally named for King</u></b> <b><u>Baudouin [[boh-DWAHN]]. Zack Clayton refereed this event, which was the subject of</u></b> <b><u>the film (*)</u> </b><em><b>When We Were Kings</b></em><b>. The rope-a-dope strategy was employed during this event, which occurred under the auspices of (*) </b>Mobutu Sese Seko. Culminating in an eighth-round knockout of George Foreman, for ten points, what 1974 fight ended with a Muhammad Ali victory in what is now the Democratic Republic of the Congo?", "answer": "The <b><u>Rumble in the Jungle</u></b> (accept descriptive answers of Muhammad <b><u>Ali</u></b>'s victory over George <b><u>Foreman</u></b> in the Republic of <b><u>Zaire</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this campaign, Raizo Tanaka sunk a destroyer with a Long Lance at</u></b> <b><u>Lunga Point. A nighttime delivery service during this campaign known as \u201crat</u></b> <b><u>transportation\u201d travelled through a location referred to as \"the Slot.\" Also known as</u></b> <b><u>Operation (+)</u> Watchtower, this campaign involved several battles fought around Savo Island. Lofton Henderson became the namesake of an airfield captured during this campaign before it was turned into (*) </b>Honiara Airport. For ten points, name this World War Two campaign fought in the Solomon Islands.", "answer": "<b><u>Guadalcanal</u></b> Campaign (accept Battle of <b><u>Guadalcanal</u></b>; accept Operation <b><u>Watchtower</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Death squads targeting this group, known as the GAL, conducted the Monbar</u></b> <b><u>Hotel attack and murdered Lasa and Zabala. This organization was targeted in the</u></b> <b><u>1970 Burgos trials which received international condemnation after six members of</u></b> <b><u>this group were (+)</u> sentenced to death. Members of this group packed Goma-2 explosives under a street, which exploded when Luis Carrero Blanco's Dart arrived in an act codenamed Operation (*) </b>Ogre. This group used the motto \"Keep up on both\" and allied with the Batasuna party. For ten points, name this Basque terrorist group.", "answer": "<b><u>ETA</u></b> (accept <b><u>Euskadi Ta Askatasuna</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The song \u201cCopper Kettle\u201d references this event, which included the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>Bower Hill. Riots in Hagerstown cascaded into Carlisle during this event, in which the</u></b> <b><u>slogan (+)</u> \u201cLiberty or Death\u201d was raised on a number of poles. Albert Gallatin regretted attending a meeting in Monongahela with leading members of this event. \u201cLight-Horse\u201d Harry Lee helped put down this event, which followed a similar event led by Daniel (*) </b>Shays. For ten points, name this revolt against an excise tax on alcohol.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion (accept synonyms for \"Rebellion\" such as \"Insurrection\" or \"Revolt\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A year before this event, the Arusha Accords were signed in a neighboring</u></b> <b><u>country, although they were voided following the assassination of Juvenal</u></b> <b><u>Habyarimana [[HOO-veh-nall hob-yah-ree-MAH-nah]]. Critics have blamed Paul (+)</u></b> <b>Kagame [[kuh-GAH-meh]] for retaliatory killings following this event. The controversial Operation Turquoise likely protected the (*) </b>perpetrators of this event, who were encouraged to \"cut down the tall trees.\" For ten points, identify this mass killing of Tutsi people by radical Hutus in a country north of Burundi.", "answer": "<b><u>Rwanda</u></b>n <b><u>Genocide</u></b> (accept <b><u>Genocide</u></b> in the Republic of <b><u>Rwanda</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tutsi</u></b> <b><u>Genocide</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}